A Register of the Nadia L. Shapiro Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Writings, 1913-1973. (Box 4)
  - "Publications Found in the Russian Transit Mail Destined for Various Latin-American Countries,", 1944 July 24. (Folder 7: 15)
  - Analysis of the Soviet Broadcasts, 1945-1947. (Folder 7: 16)
  - "Out of this World,", 1946 April. (Folder 7: 17)
  - "Preliminary Glossary of Soviet Terminology: Russian - English,", 1947-1950. (Folder 7: 18)
  - "Russian-English Glossary of Motor-Transport and Related Terms," U.S. Department of Commerce, Office of Technical Services, Joint Publications Research Service, 1963 June. (Folder 7: 19)
  - Description of the ship model representing a 14th century Genoese galley, 1969 February 2. (Folder 7: 20)
  - "Memo on My Connection with the Rezanov Book and on My Ownership of Two of the Volumes,", 1971.; See Subject File/Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
  - "Dopolnitel'nye svedenia o sud'be nekotorykh iz knig, privezennykh Nikolaem Petrovichem Rezanovym na Aliasku,", 1973.
- Subject File, 1924-1951. (Box 8)
  Autographs, clippings and other printed matter, correspondence, essays, excerpts from documents, notes, stories, studies, writings, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Alaska ߝ History, 1927-1946.; See also Photographs/Prints/Subject file (Folder 8: 1)
  - Autographs of well-known people, n.d. (Folder 8: 2)
  - Clarke, Edward W., 1923(?) (Folder 8: 3)
  - Honcharenko, Agapius, 1868-1939.; See also Photographs/Prints/Subject file/Agapius Honcharenko (Folder 8: 4)
  - Japan
    - General, 1929.; See also Photographs (Folder 8: 5)
    - Secret service, 1935-1943.; See also Photographs/Subject file/Japan (Folder 8: 6)
      Includes photographic prints of agreement, and excerpt from the promissory note of His Imperial Majesty Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich to General Dmitrii Khorvat regarding state funds that were in possession of General Kolchak during the Russian Civil War, n.d.
  - Kourennoff, Pavel Matveevich, 1944-1945 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Mikhailov, Captain, n.d. (Folder 8: 8)
  - Mongolia, n.d. (Folder 8: 9)
  - Nitman family, 1928-1937 (Folder 8: 10)
  - "Pacific Story," Unidentified writing, n.d. (Folder 8: 11)
  - Refugees ߝ Russian, 1924-1941 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich, 1934-1973. (Folder 8: 13-14)
    Includes 1 photographic image of a wild ocean, n.d.
  - Russia ߝ Revolution, (1917-1921) (Box 9)
    - General, 1924-1951 (Folder 9: 1)
    - Alekseevskii, Aleksandr Nikolaevich (Folder 9: 2)
    - White Army officers and soldiers in foreign armies, 1934 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Russian bell - Russian Cathedral - San Francisco, 1923.; See also Photographs/Subject file/Russian Church in San Francisco (Folder 9: 4)
    Includes photograph.
  - Russian Orthodox Church, 1924-1935 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Russian poetry, n.d. (Folder 9: 6)
  - Russians in foreign countries
    - China, 1924-1944 (Folder 9: 7)
    - Great Britain, 1929 (Folder 9: 8)
    - Paraguay, 1934 (Folder 9: 9)
    - United States, 1924 (Folder 9: 10)
  - Tolstoy, Leo (reminiscences), 1924 (Folder 9: 11)
  - World War (1914-1918) ߝ Russia, 1925-1929.; See also Photographs/Prints/General/Russian Imperial Army (Folder 9: 12)
- Printed Matter, 1913-1963.
  Clippings, leaflets, magazines, newspapers, and pamphlets, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings, 1922-1963 (Folder 9: 13-16)
  - Leaflets, n.d., 1937 (Folder 9: 17)
  - Magazines, 1913-1935 (Folder 9: 18-19)
  - Newspapers, 1920-1954 (Folder 9: 20-21)
  - Newspapers, 1920-1954 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Pamphlets
    - Untitled, n.d. (Folder 10: 2)
    - Andrews, Lilian, Youth of the Happy Land, New York (Folder 10: 3)
    - Great Photographs of World War II: Selected by the Editors of the Reader's Digest, New York, n.d. (Folder 10: 4)
    - Kratkii russko-iaponskii slovar, Osaka (Japan), n.d. (Folder 10: 5)
    - Mintslov, S. R., Sinodik bibliotek, arkhiov i kollektsii, pogibshikh vo vremia Velikoi voiny i revoliutsii, Berlin, n.d. (Folder 10: 6)
    - Maslov, Georgii, Untitled poetry, 1919(?). (Folder 10: 7)
    - Notice, Fondation Egyptologique Reine Elisabeth, Brussels, 1923 (Folder 10: 8)
    - Le lotus bleu (Fondé par H. P. Blavatsky), Revue Théosophique, Paris, 1924 (Folder 10: 9)
    - Shumakov, B. A., Limannoe oroshenie, Moscow, 1925 (Folder 10: 10)
    - The Interpreter, New York, 1925 (Folder 10: 11)
    - Dynnik, Tatiana, Krepostnye aktery, Moscow, 1927 (Folder 10: 12)
    - Gorchakov, M., Duke, Itogi politiki mitropolitov Sergiia i Evlogiia, Paris, 1929 (Folder 10: 13)
    - De Leon, Daniel, Russia in Revolution, New York, 1930 (Folder 10: 14)
    - The Report of the Harbin Relief Committee of Russian Emigrants in North Manchuria (China), Harbin, 1930 (Folder 10: 15)
    - Vitsilli, P., Kratkaia istoriia russkoi literatury ot Pushkina do nashego vremeni (Chast' vtoraia), Sofia, 1934 (Folder 10: 16)
    - Robson, R. W., Communism: An Outline for Everyone, Sydney, 1943(?) (Folder 10: 17)
    - La parole indépendante: Recueil politique, social, littéraire, Sous la rédaction de S. P. Melgounoff, Paris, 1945 (Folder 10: 18)
  - Miscellany (Folder 10: 19)
- Art Work, 1926.
  Drawings and portrait, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - 2 drawings by Alexander Shwartz (Folder 10: 20)
  - 1 portrait of Nadia Shapiro(?) by Max Vollmberg, 1926 (Folder 10: 21)
- Postcards, n.d.
  Postcards depicting art work and scenes in Siberia and Japan
  - 27 postcards depicting famous Russian paintings, n.d. (Folder 10: 22)
  - 2 postcards depicting Nedashkovskii paintings, n.d. (Folder 10: 23)
  - 4 postcards depicting the Siberian city Irkutsk, n.d. (Folder 10: 24)
  - 1 postcard depicting the Baikal region (East Siberia) - Unlicensed gold miners washing gold in secret, n.d. (Folder 10: 25)
  - 8 postcards depicting Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 26)
- Photographs, 1916-1965.
  149 prints and two negatives depicting Nadia Shapiro, her family and friends, Russian culture in Alaska, and some aspects of Japanese life and history
  - Prints
    - General
      - Unidentified (Folder 10: 27)
      - 1 print depicting Ivan Frisen, n.d. (Folder 10: 28)
      - 1 print depicting Ivan Frisen and family (Folder 10: 29)
      - 8 prints depicting Barrett Willoughby, n.d. (Folder 10: 30)
      - 1 print depicting Barrett Willoughby and Bob (Folder 10: 31)
      - 3 prints depicting Jacob Febesoff and family (Folder 10: 32)
      - 1 print depicting Vinokuroff, Michael Z., See Correspondence/Vinokuroff, Michael Z.
      - 5 prints depicting Captain Kristian Klengenberg and his family (Folder 10: 33)
      - 1 print depicting Siberian burials near Kiarhta, n.d. (Folder 10: 34)
      - 1 print depicting Anadyr, n.d. (Folder 10: 35)
      - 1 print depicting interior of a Japanese house, n.d. (Folder 10: 36)
      - 1 print depicting seven-floor building in Marunouchi, Tokyo, n.d. (Folder 10: 37)
      - 1 print depicting two Geisha girls at a Botan show, by Eishi, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 38)
      - 1 print of sculpture miniatures depicting scenes of Japanese everyday life, n.d. (Folder 10: 39)
      - 1 print depicting Naoe Fenshimi, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 40)
      - 1 print depicting Takako Irie, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 41)
      - 2 prints depicting Goro Kawabe, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 42)
      - 1 Print depicting Hajime Masuda, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 43)
      - 1 print depicting Shizue Natoukawa, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 44)
      - 1 print depicting Denjiro Ohkorhi, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 45)
      - 1 print depicting Tokihiko Okada, Japan, n.d. (Folder 10: 46)
      - 1 print depicting Tokihiko Okada and Takako Irie, taken from a scene in the "Raid," Japan (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - 1 print depicting Ranko Sawa, Japan, n.d. (Folder 11: 2)
      - 1 print depicting Kohji Shima, Japan, n.d. (Folder 11: 3)
      - 1 print depicting Hisako Takihana, Japan, n.d. (Folder 11: 4)
      - 1 print depicting Yoshoko Tokugawa, Japan, n.d. (Folder 11: 5)
      - 1 print depicting Yohko Umemura, Japan, n.d. (Folder 11: 6)
      - 9 prints depicting various events in the Russian Imperial Army, 1916 (?) (Folder 11: 7)
      - 3 prints depicting Jean Paine (Spray) Helm, 1920s (Folder 11: 8)
      - 1 print of abbot of Buddhist temple in Washington. "The Reverend G. Mapo of Yamamoto, Japan, Abbott of Ryutakiy Buddhist temple, photographed with Ambassador Haniharria of Japan as they called at the White House to visit President Harding," International Newsreel Photo, 1923 May 4 (Folder 11: 9)
      - 1 print of scene "amidst the ruins of Yokohama, where natives are trying to restore some semblance of home. The picture shows the baby-san getting it's [sic] bath," International Newsreel Photo, 1923 November 11 (Folder 11: 10)
      - 1 print of bear taken on ice floor in Arctic Ocean, 1925(?) (Folder 11: 11)
      - 3 prints depicting "dogs and dog teams running on frozen ocean on the strait between Herschel Island and mainland,", 1925(?) (Folder 11: 12)
      - 5 prints depicting "Prince Albert Sound. Pair of blond Eskimos in their dance clothes,", 1925 (Folder 11: 13)
      - 4 prints depicting natives from Victoria Island, 1925 (Folder 11: 14)
      - 5 prints depicting inhabitants and scenes from Herschel Island, 1925 (Folder 11: 15)
      - 5 prints depicting Barrett Willoughby, 1928 (Folder 11: 16)
      - 3 prints depicting Barrett Willoughby, 1929 (Folder 11: 17)
      - 1 print depicting Boris Volkov, 1928 (Folder 11: 18)
      - 2 prints depicting Lawrence Spray (Jean (Spray) Helm's son), 1930-1931 (Folder 11: 19)
      - 1 print depicting Constance Dixon, 1933 (Folder 11: 20)
      - 1 print depicting Jean Paine (Spray) Helm, 1934.; See Correspondence/Helm, Jean
    - Biographical file
      - 8 prints depicting Nadia Shapiro, n.d. (Folder 11: 21)
      - 1 print depicting Nadia Shapiro and Barrett Willoughby (Folder 11: 22)
      - 1 print of Robert Prosser, Nadia Shapiro, and Eric Nelson (Folder 11: 23)
      - 1 print of Nadia Shapiro and unidentified person (Folder 11: 24)
      - 5 prints depicting Nadia Shapiro in Japan, 1920 (Folder 11: 25)
      - 2 prints depicting Nadia Shapiro (passport pictures), 1965 (Folder 11: 26)
      - 1 print depicting Lazar Shapiro(?), n.d. (Folder 11: 27)
      - 1 print depicting Mary Shapiro, n.d. (Folder 11: 28)
      - 3 prints depicting Mary Shapiro, 1925-1934 (Folder 11: 29)
      - 1 print depicting Mary Shapiro, 1961.; See Biographical File/Correspondence (family)/Shapiro, Mary
    - Subject file., See also Subject File/Alaska
      - Alaska
        - 2 prints depicting watchtower on Island of Rocking Moon, Kodiak (Folder 11: 30)
        - 1 print depicting Island of Rocking Moon (Folder 11: 31)
        - 1 print depicting convict wall at Kodiak, n.d. (Folder 11: 32)
        - 1 print of "old millstone of the Russians and little muzzle loading cannon brought to Kodiak by Grigorii Shelekhov in 1794," (Folder 11: 33)
        - 1 print of "Russian Staff House at Kodiak, boarded over now. On top of this Russians of Alexander I use [sic] to be....," (Folder 11: 34)
        - 1 print of Russian Church in Kodiak. "Church of Resurrection first built in 1795. Present edifice 1894,", n.d. (Folder 11: 35)
        - 1 print of a "bell from a Russian Church at Atka Island ߝ farthest west church in the world," (Folder 11: 36)
        - 1 print of Peter the Great. "This was cut from its frame in the old castle of Sitka of the time of the transferee, and lasted until 1918, when the man who took it brought it out, sold it to the Governor of Alaska," (Folder 11: 37)
        - 1 print of "interior of the Russian Church at Kodiak ߝ first Russian Church built in Alaska (1794),", n.d. (Folder 11: 38)
        - 1 print of "Devil's Prongs of Kodiak named by Russians, but now called by missionaries 'Three Sisters,'", n.d. (Folder 11: 39)
        - 1 print of "interior of the Colonial Administrator (1790-1818) Aleksandr Baranov's house (see icons)," (Folder 11: 40)
        - 1 print of Community Grindstone, used by the Russian colony in 1830, the Photo Shop Studio, Sitka, Alaska (Folder 11: 41)
        - 1 print of Russian Church at Wizinki, Alaska, n.d. (Folder 11: 42)
        - 1 print of "Kodiak millstone and muzzleloader both brought to America from Russia by Aleksandr Baranov, Kodiak founded 1791 by Baranov," (Folder 11: 43)
        - 1 print depicting "place where Bering crew landed on Kayak Island to take water," (Folder 11: 44)
        - 1 print depicting view from the "bell tower of the old Russian Church at Kodiak,", n.d. (Folder 11: 45)
        - 1 print depicting Creole grave, Afognac Island. "Inside box is a rush light, which is replenished as often as affection dictates. Cross at the top of grave so resurrected one may see it at once on sitting up," (Folder 11: 46)
        - 2 prints depicting Kodiak old graveyard, n.d. (Folder 11: 47)
        - 1 prints depicting a view overlooking the "Harbor of St. Peter and Paul at Kodiak, taken from in front of old Russian Staff House," (Folder 11: 48)
        - 2 prints of "Maksim Pachin, son of a Russian Naval Doctor, Kodiak,", n.d. (Folder 11: 49)
        - 1 print depicting "Aleuts putting up wild hay, Kodiak,", n.d. (Folder 11: 50)
        - 1 print depicting "Hotel in Kodiak ߝ log house built by Russians and boarded over," (Folder 11: 51)
        - 1 print depicting "a bell, cast on the gale-swept, winter shore of the North Pacific by Greek Catholic Russian missionaries, was found in an ever summery California. Its inscription is: This bell was cast on the island of Kodiak on the month of January 1796 under the direction of Arch-Mandrite Joseph and in the presence of Director Aleksander Baranov," Photo Shop Allie Harriman (Folder 11: 52)
        - 1 print depicting portraits of East Russian Governor Prince Dimitri Maksourov, Princess Maksourova, Metropolitan of Moscow and Kolomna Ioann Veniaminov Innocent, Captain F. V. Koskul, Captain John F. Emmons, and U.S. Commissioner General Rousseau (Folder 11: 53)
      - Honcharenko, Agapius
        - 2 prints depicting Agapius Honcharenko., See also Subject File/Honcharenko, Agapius (Folder 11: 54)
      - Japan - Secret Service
        - 7 prints of photographs of agreement and excerpt from the promissory note of His Imperial Majesty Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich to General Dmitrii Khorvat regarding state funds that were in possession of General Kolchak during the Russian Civil War (Folder 11: 55)
          See Subject File/Japan/Secret Service
      - Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich (Folder 11: 56)
        - 1 print depicting a wild ocean, n.d.; See also Subject File/ Rezanov, Nikolai Petrovich
      - Russian Orthodox Church
        - 1 print depicting a Russian Church in San Francisco, n.d.; See also Subject File/Russian bell (Folder 11: 57)
        - 1 print depicting an Orthodox-Catholic Church, n.d.; See also Subject File/Russian bell (Folder 11: 58)
    - Writings
      - "Comrades Together.", See also Writings/"Comrades Together." (Folder 11: 59)
        1 print depicting Fedor Ivanovich Alferov in a page's (Pazhes) unit uniform, n.d. Copy was made from the original taken during the Russo-Japanese War, retaken in Saint Petersburg in 1925
  - Negatives, 1923. (Folder 11: 60)
    2 negatives depicting Molokans (family?) from "Russian Mountain"
- Sound recordings (Phonorecords), 1946 (Record cabinet)
  - Nadia Shapiro sound recording in Russian, 1946 July 6 - August 26 (Record cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 90004_a_0002891
    Side A label reads: Rec. No. 56967/Overseas Branch/Office of War Information/San Francisco Office/Title: Nadia Shapiro (Russian)(dub)/Date: 8/26/46. Side B label reads: No. 1-B/Date: July 6/Time: 2200 GMT/Program: Russian Test/Language: Russian/Announcer: Nadia OPR: Fhoare
  - Nadia Shapiro sound recording in Russian, 1946 August 8 (Record cabinet)
    Use copy reference number: 90004_a_0002892
    Label reads: Rec. No. 56783/Overseas Branch/Office of War Information/San Francisco Office/Title: Nadia Shapiro (Russian)/ Part 1 of 1/Recorded Date: 8/8/46 Time: 10:30 AM
- Incremental Materials (Box 12)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.